Finding aid to American Association of University Women. Massachusetts Division records SSC.MS.00333
Sophia Smith Collection
American Association of University Women. Massachusetts Division records
1933-1990
Sophia Smith Collection
American Association of University Women. Massachusetts Division
SSC.MS.00333
3 boxes (1.25 linear feet)
The American Association of University Women (AAUW) was founded in 1882 to unite alumnae of different institutions for "practical educational work." The records of the Massachusetts Division of the AAUW include histories, correspondence, reports, clippings, publications and other printed material from western Massachusetts AAUW branches.
Biographical / Historical
The American Association of University Women (AAUW) was founded in 1882 to unite alumnae of different institutions for "practical educational work." Originally open to graduates of institutions accredited by the AAUW, it is now open to women graduates of regionally accredited U.S. colleges and universities of foreign institutions recognized by the International Federation of University Women.
In March 1986 the Massachusetts State Division of the AAUW and its local branches entered into a joint acquisition agreement with four separate archival repositories in Massachusetts. The Sophia Smith Collection agreed to collect the records of the branches located in Berkshire, Franklin, Hampden, Hampshire, and Worcester Counties; the Essex Institute, the records of the Essex County branches; Wheaton College, the records of branches in Barnstable, Bristol, Dukes, Nantucket, and Plymouth Counties; and the Schlesinger Library at Radliffe, the records of the branches of Middlesex, Norfolk, and Suffolk counties as well as the State Division records.
Scope and Contents
These records document the western Massachusetts AAUW branches (Berkshire, Franklin, Hampden, and Hampshire Counties). Materials include histories, correspondence, reports, clippings, publications and other printed materials.
Related Material
Associated materials can be found in the American Association of University Women Records; the Connecticut Valley Branch Records; and the Worcester Branch Records.
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveat: Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.
Accruals
This collection is comprised of the following accessions, some of which may not have accession records. Accession numbers: 86S-26, 03S-61. Accessions were received on the following dates: 1986, 2003-10-06.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
A small quantity of records of the Berkshire, Franklin, Hampden, Hampshire, and Worcester Branches was transferred to Smith College from the Schlesinger Library in March 1986. The portion from the Connecticut Valley Branch was removed and combined with other records of that branch to make up a separate record group. An additional accession of Worcester Branch records was transferred from the American Antiquarian Society in March 1989. These were combined with the previously transferred Worcester records and made into a separate record group.
Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--Massachusetts; Women college graduates--Massachusetts--History--Sources; Women--Education--Massachusetts--History--Sources; Women in the professions--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Histories; Publications; correspondence; reports; clippings; American Association of University Women. Massachusetts Division--History--Sources; Newhall, Claudette; Kilson, Marion; American Association of University Women. Massachusetts Division
- Franklin County
  - Histories and programs, 1935-1975 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1951-1958 (Box 1)
- North Adams area
  - President's reports, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
- Northern Massachusetts
  - Histories, annual reports, 1933-1974; 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, newsletters, 1962-1974 (Box 1)
  - Newsletter, 1975 (Box 1)
- Greater Springfield, 1971 (Box 1)
- Sterling, 1968-1976
- Webster area
  - Histories, 1957-1966; 1986 (Box 1)
  - Histories, 1966-1974; 1978 (Box 1)